Okay, good morning church. It's great to see all of you here today. Welcome again to our Sunday celebration.
As we get started this morning, I'm excited to share God's Word with you.
And if you can open to Ephesians chapter 1, that would be great.
If we haven't met yet, my name is Pete. I'm one of the pastors here at HMCC.
And I'm excited to share the Word of God with all of us this morning.
And I also just want to give a special welcome to any of you who are new, joining us for the first time today,
checking things out here in our spiritual family.
We hope you have a great time here today getting connected to God.
also to the church community around you. And yeah, if you'd like to meet after the celebration,
get to know one another, see what God, you know, I'd love to hear what God's doing in your life
and hear your story as well. As we get into today's message, I'm excited because, you know,
we're just at the beginning of a new season and jumping into this new theme of higher calling
that we've been talking about. And actually, just one quick mention before we get into it
is some of you might have noticed as you came in today, we had quite a bit of like new concrete
work done outside over the past week or so. And I'm very grateful for that, partly because
there were some cracks and things that needed to be fixed and needed to get remedied. And so we were
finally able to get that done. We also hope it'll really help with keeping water out of the
basement, out of the bathrooms, out of the kitchen, out of those areas where we were having some leaking
problems before. So grateful for that. But while it was going on, I think some of you also heard
that the contractors hit a pipe and caused a massive leak and evidently somebody like put up
the bat signal on the top of the t-center and a bunch of people came out and started helping and
so i want to just appreciate many of the people that just kind of showed up to mop up to get rid
to deal with all that water thankfully nothing really got permanently damaged except a few ceiling
tiles because everybody just jumped in so quickly to help and so i just really appreciate everyone
who jumped in to serve, and thankful that we can see not just concrete work getting done,
but even the church family coming together to serve together.
Can we just appreciate real quick those who did jump in to serve?
Yeah, and as I mentioned, last week we did introduce our new theme for this year, which
is higher calling, and talking about rising above temporary pursuits to live for God's
eternal purposes, and I think even those things like just jumping in to serve, being available
that way. That's a small picture of that higher calling. But as we get into today's message, I think
what we want to really get into is that it's not just about these things that we do and these things
we do for God. It really starts at a much deeper place than that. And as we get ready to get into
Ephesians chapter 1 here, we'll be covering a few more verses this morning. Maybe I could ask you to
think about it this way. Like, just imagine that you're walking around town here somewhere in Ann
Arbor. And as you're walking around, you pass by a new building under construction. Hard to imagine,
I'm sure. We don't have much construction in Ann Arbor, do we? No, it's all over the place, right?
Imagine that you walk by a building, and you see three guys working on the building, and they're
all doing the same thing. But you stop at each person and ask them, hey, what are you doing?
So imagine you stop at the first person and say, hey, what are you doing? And the person says,
I'm laying bricks. Okay, I was laying bricks. And then let's say you walk to the second person.
Say, hey, what are you doing? I'm just clocking in, collecting a paycheck, paying the bills.
Okay, he's paying the bills, getting his paycheck. And you walk to a third person. Say, hey, what
are you doing? Third person says, I'm building a grand cathedral. Now, I don't know if we have
any cathedrals under construction in Ann Arbor, but hopefully you can just kind of sense even
those different responses. Different people kind of have a different sort of understanding,
perspective heart toward the things that we do and for all of us here as we build relationship
with God as we participate in the life of the church as we want to live for this higher calling
I think there's a lot of stuff that needs to be shifted inside of us about how we approach
the life that we live and so as we get into today's passage in Ephesians 1 we want to really
talk about like how what does it look like to rise up and see the full purpose of God in our lives
and what we need to recognize is it's not first about what we do, but about who we are through
faith in Jesus Christ. And so I'm going to go ahead and read Ephesians 1, 3 to 6 today. That's
all we're covering for this morning. I'll go ahead and read this for us. It says this,
Blessed be the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, who has blessed us in Christ with every
spiritual blessing in the heavenly places, even as he chose us in him before the foundation of the
world, that we should be holy and blameless before him. In love, he predestined us for adoption to
himself as sons through Jesus Christ according to the purpose of his will, to the praise of his
glorious grace with which he has blessed us in the beloved. Amen. We'll pause there and we pray for
us one more time. Jesus, we invite you to come and speak to us today through your holy word. We thank
you for the good gift of your word, that through your word, Lord, you reveal yourself to us. You
you lift us up into this higher calling that you have for us, God. You reveal not only who you are,
but who you are calling us to be, and out of who you're calling us to be, how you're calling us
to follow you. So please speak to us today, each one of us personally, God, but even all of us
together as the family of church, of the church, and lead us into that together today, God. We
thank you so much. It's in Jesus' name that we pray. Amen. Amen. Okay, so as we get into this
here this morning, we're going to start off with talking about God's blessing, and then at the end
we'll talk about our response to the blessing that God gives us. So what is that here as we get
into today's passage? The first thing I want to introduce for us is just this idea that God's
blessing in this passage is about inheritance and adoption. God's blessing is about inheritance
and adoption. And specifically, we find out in verse 3, it says that God has blessed us in Christ.
And here as we start to think about that, like what is this blessing? What's it look like?
I want to draw a clear distinction here, but there are different kinds of blessings.
Partly, there are general blessings, or what people might actually call common grace,
that is just out there for all of humanity to enjoy.
These are things like the air we breathe, the food that we eat, beautiful sunsets, family, friends,
things like that, that is just out there for all of humanity to enjoy.
And those are great things, common grace, common blessings given to everybody.
But here in this passage, what Paul is talking about is not just those common things that everybody can enjoy.
These are specific blessings in Christ.
And he's describing how for those of us who are in Christ, that we then receive these blessings as an inheritance.
And we receive these things by faith in Jesus and what it is that he has done for us.
And right up front, I want to make that really clear.
especially knowing that in this room there's some of us that maybe you've been following Christ and
placed your faith in him a long time ago but for some of us here maybe you're really new to the
Christian faith and you're not sure what this is about and I think for many people they think that
Christianity is about like all these things that we do but the Christian faith is primarily about
what God has done for us and what we find out when we go through the scriptures is that Jesus is the
eternal son of God who was born into this world in human flesh that he lived a life of complete love
and obedience to God. He died on the cross as an atoning sacrifice for our sins, and then he rose
again in victory over death. And when we place our faith in him, that out of those historical
realities that actually happened, then that brings a spiritual change in our lives. Now we are in
Christ through faith, and we can then receive these blessings that God has for us. Author Graham
Goldworthy, he describes it this way. He says, only the message that another true and obedient
human being has come on our behalf, that he has lived for us the kind of life we should live but
can't, that he has paid fully the penalty we deserve for the life we do live but shouldn't,
only this message can give assurance that we have peace with God through our Lord Jesus Christ.
And so as we think about that, where I want us to really dig into and start is that Paul wants
us to understand not only what Jesus has done for us, but what that means for us, and how do we like
live in those truths, and again, for some of you here that maybe you're exploring the Christian
faith today, you're asking questions, maybe a friend invited you here, we're so glad that
you're here, I would encourage you, really look at that, and think about, okay, maybe there are
things you can enjoy in life that everybody gets to enjoy, but can you know today that because of
what God did for, not just for the people around you, but for you through the life and death and
resurrection of his son, Jesus Christ, that there is actually a spiritual blessing that God desires
to bestow in your life that we're going to be talking about through the rest of today and even
after that. And so we taught that God's blessed us in Christ, and specifically it says in verse
three that he's given us every spiritual blessing, every spiritual blessing. I mean, there are none
in reserve. There are none that are held back for somebody else but not for you. And that's
something like, I don't know that all of us really have that mindset. A lot of us look at those
around us and we have maybe this thing inside of us that says, oh, that other person is more
blessed than me. Why does that other person seem like maybe God loves them just a little bit more
than he loves me? They seem like they have more than I do. But here we find out every spiritual
blessing is given to those who are in Christ. Can you turn to somebody next to you and say,
you get them all. This is the inheritance that we receive when we are in Jesus Christ. And Paul's
specifically referring to these blessings that we're going to be talking about here in today's
passage and even through the rest of chapters 1 and 2 in Ephesians. So we're not even going to
get to all of it today. We're just covering a small portion. But these spiritual blessings that
we have, they're intended for us to really like know, again, not first about what we do, but first
about who we are. And that's why even as we start thinking about this, I just want to give reference
to like a couple resources that we end up coming back to repeatedly a lot in our church, just for
you to maybe revisit, maybe to pray through, to reflect on, to journal about. A couple of these
that I think are really helpful for us, one is if you go to hmcc.tech slash identity, that's a
a list of who I am in Christ.
It's from a book by Neil Anderson.
And for some of you,
maybe that would be really good to review.
Another is hmcc.tech slash birthright.
This is from our Freedom Class manual that we use.
It's talking about the Christian's birthright
that we receive, again, in Christ, by faith in Christ.
This is now who we are,
these spiritual blessings given to us.
We're gonna go through in a lot finer detail,
giving a lot more attention
to the things here in Ephesians.
But there's so much there
that's revealed to us in the scriptures
about these spiritual blessings that we have in Jesus Christ,
and that might be good for us to actually review,
and then realize that here in this passage,
it says that every spiritual blessing,
it's given to us in the heavenly places.
That means that these are spiritual blessings
that are eternal, transcendent, and secure,
that nobody can take these blessings away from you.
It's not like someone can come steal it away
or that we're gonna lose it somehow.
No, these are given to us in Christ,
in the heavenly places, and those are some things that we can truly hold on to. Now, with all of
that, again, we're going to unpack that a lot more as we go on. So this is just a big umbrella term
right now, these spiritual blessings. But as we think about that, why do we receive these spiritual
blessings from God? Why do we receive these? Why are we blessed by Him? And I'm pausing there for
a second, because I think for many of us, whether we know, like, the right answer or not, a lot of
times, the mindset we get into is, well, if I'm blessed by God, it's because I prayed enough,
maybe because I read the Bible enough, maybe because I went to church enough,
maybe because I just didn't screw up like other people do. And we get in this mindset like somehow
it's about something about us is the reason that we receive these blessings. But what we see here,
what we're going to spend a little time here digging into, the actual reason we receive these
spiritual blessings from God is because God has chosen and predestined us. That's why. Because God
has chosen and predestined us. And we're going to pause on these terms here for a second and not
rush past them because I know that, I mean, like when I look at these words, I think these are
beautiful words, but that these words tend to bring up some really big questions among Christians
and, you know, it tends to lead to some long conversations. In fact, I've talked to many people
here within our church family that have shared with me, like, oh, yeah, in my life group, we had
this long conversation about, like, what does predestined mean? I had this argument with a friend
about free will and whether we have it or not. Like, these are complicated and difficult ideas
that we want to spend some time to dig into here today, and I know for many of us, we hear these
terms, chosen, predestined, God doing these things, and maybe it's confusing. Just like, I don't know
what that means. What's that about? For others of us, maybe it's actually offensive.
this idea that God chose something for us God predestined us for something in some way and I
didn't get to make my own decision on that for some of us that's an offensive idea that we're
very uncomfortable with or we don't like for some of us it can even become a divisive topic
you have one view on it somebody else has a different view maybe there's a conflict a division
that comes up because you're seeing things differently.
So I just want to recognize that
and try to dig into this at least a little bit here today
because as we start encountering these terms today,
we're going to come across them a lot more
through the rest of Ephesians.
And so I'm going to kind of pause here
to make sure that we at least have some understanding
of what we're talking about here.
So how should we understand God's sovereignty?
How should we understand his choice, his predestination?
How should we understand human responsibility
and freedom in light of that, let's take a long detour here and dig into this a little bit before
we go further. And by the way, again, not all of us are from the same backgrounds. Maybe if you're
coming from more of a secular background, like I grew up in, maybe you're used to hearing like
philosophers talk about these things with ideas like determinism or free will or stuff like that.
And some related ideas, not exactly the same thing. But as we dig into this, I think most
Christians approach these questions from either a Reformed or an Arminian theological tradition.
And if you've heard the term Reformed before, this is often associated with people like John
Calvin or Calvinism. There are other prominent figures as well. And then Arminianism, that's
associated with Jacobus Arminius. And, you know, people, there's strong theological traditions
there as well. And as we get into that, I want to recognize that a lot of conversations and
questions around this, tend to kind of devolve into mischaracterizing these different positions,
just having kind of superficial understandings of them, throwing straw man arguments at each other,
tends to be really unhealthy. I'm going to try as best as I can to give you just an overview
here of just kind of basic approach to this, and then hey, you can go talk about it in your
life group, and you'll all work it out together, okay? So how do we understand God's sovereignty
and human responsibility? I'm going to throw up a few things in a table on screen here, and as we
start, first, what is the Reformed view on this? First, the Reformed view is that God is the
primary transcendent cause of all history, and humans act as secondary causes. So God causes
things in real ways, and humans also cause things in real ways. There's a dual causation
happening there. Now, what does this look like? I'm going to try to give you some analogies,
knowing that analogies are always imperfect. So it's an imperfect analogy, but I hope it helps.
Back about 10 years ago or so, my son Nicholas, he started taking judo lessons.
And here's a picture of him doing some judo, by the way.
This is not when he started.
This is actually like a couple years in.
So imagine him even smaller, okay?
Smaller, even cuter.
So he started taking judo.
And I remember the first time we took him to this judo studio and met the sensei and
trying to decide, okay, is this something we want to try out or not?
And so we have a little conversation with the sensei first.
and then he brings Nicholas out on the mat
and says, okay, let's try something.
And so he brings Nicholas out there on the mat
and he shows him how to do like a judo,
like the way you kind of do a judo stance
and set up with the other person,
which is basically that you hold onto their shirt
like this with your right hand
and you hold onto their arm with the other hand
and you're kind of like holding like this
and each person is holding each other this way.
And the sensei instructs him and says,
okay, now you're gonna reach under my shoulder,
Grab my uniform here.
Grab me like this.
Hold on to my arm, my wrist right here.
And he kind of gets Nicholas in position like this.
And by the way, Nicholas is like five years old.
He's probably like 35 pounds or something.
And the sensei is like a, he's actually like a world level like sensei guy, judo guy.
And so he's like 200 pounds of pure muscle.
Okay, so imagine me but more muscular.
Okay, and so he's got Nicholas.
Nicholas is like down here and he's up here.
He's got Nicholas holding over his shoulder.
and grabbing his wrist, and he says, okay, Nicholas, when you're ready, lean forward and pull on my arm.
And so Nicholas leans forward, pulls on his arm, and the sensei from behind, like, vaults over him
and slams down on the ground in front of him on his back. Bam! And like, Nicholas, you should have seen him.
He turned and looked at Gina and I, and he's just like, he's like, I'm tough, right?
And that sealed the deal.
It's like, okay, we're doing judo.
So we did that for a few years.
But I share that because, again, like, the sensei had a way he wanted that to go, right?
I think he knew what he was doing.
He's like, man, if I give this kid a show and, like, you know, he's going to want to do judo, right?
But he's like, okay, I have a plan for this, right?
I'm going to show the kid how to do it.
I'm going to let him know, hey, when you're ready, you go ahead.
You lean over and you pull.
And then he jumps over and makes that throw happen, right?
The sense I planned it, the sense I was kind of guiding it all along,
was Nicholas actually involved in the throw?
Did he actually make decisions in it?
Did he actually move and participate?
Yeah, he did.
So dual causation, two at the same time.
So this, again, imperfect illustration.
If you try to make that fit perfectly what we're talking about,
you're going to run into problems.
But in a general way, this idea that God works with humanity,
God in his sovereignty, and then what happens from there,
how do we understand this with respect to sin and human failure? Well, God is the efficient
cause of all good, and human sin is the deficient cause of evil. And God is not the author or
approver of sin, but permits sin without violating human accountability. Okay, so that means anything
good, everything out there that's good, God is the efficient cause, meaning the primary cause
of all good things, because God is goodness, God is holy love, everything good comes from him
as gifts from the Father, right, and when things go wrong in the world, that deficient cause is
human sin, because we turn and rebel against God, okay, but we're accountable for our actions,
even though as across this, God purposes even wicked human acts for a redemptive outcome,
So just like I referred to last year, or last year, last week, in Genesis 50, like, Joseph
is able to say to his brothers, hey, you meant this for evil, but God meant it for good. So
something wicked that humans are doing, God is able to redeem that and use that positively
for his purposes. And God predestines and unconditionally chooses those who will be
saved by his grace without reliance on human will. So humans have no decision, really no decision
making in the process, but it's just like God makes this choice, and humans then just respond
to God's predestined choice for those people, okay? That's more of a reformed view. Now, the
Arminian view, some of you may be familiar with this, maybe not. In the Arminian view, God foresees
and foreknows all of history, but his foreknowledge does not necessitate all events, okay? So with
this, I do this when I'm driving, or at least I try to, okay? Another imperfect analogy, especially
when I'm driving on Washtenaw,
if you guys have driven on Washtenaw, like coming from out
that way and coming toward campus,
and you guys know there's like four lanes, and there's a lot
of traffic going each way, right?
A lot of traffic. And when I'm
driving toward campus, I know that
there are certain intersections where
somebody's probably going to pause
and turn left, and there's not a turn lane there,
and so all the traffic is going to get backed up behind them, right?
So when I'm driving up there, I always look ahead,
and I'm looking, is there a left turn
signal on anywhere up there?
Is somebody going to back up the traffic?
and I'm going to get stuck behind them.
I'm going to miss the light
and I'm going to get a couple minutes delayed.
And so I'm like looking for that.
And if I see that, I'm like, okay.
And then sometimes I don't see a turn signal,
but there's still a lot of cars in front of me
and I'm like, I know these Ann Arbor drivers.
Even though they don't put on their turn signal,
they're still going to turn left.
They're going to stop everybody without signaling.
They're going to hold everybody up
even though they didn't do that.
And so I'm like, okay, I'm going to go ahead
and get in the right lane
so I'm not held up when somebody inevitably does that.
And I'm usually vindicated in my choice.
I get up closer there and yep,
that person slammed on the brakes, everyone's backed up behind them, they didn't even bother
to use their turn signal, and I'm like, yes, I made the right choice. I knew what those people
were going to do, right? And I go on ahead, right? This is, okay, this is in a very small way,
right? God is doing this through the whole course of history, right? He looks ahead, and he sees
all the possible outcomes, and he knows what human beings are like, and he knows the choices people
are going to make. He foreknows all of this, right? But he is not forcing any of it. Because we see
here in this view, God grants humans libertarian free will and permits human rebellion. So libertarian
free will, that means like truly free choice. God is not constraining human choices. He's letting
them do what they're going to do, but he knows what they're going to do. Okay, that's what this
view says. And then within that, sin is solely caused by misuse of human freedom. God does not
cause sin, either directly, indirectly, or conditionally. Okay, so when that person
hits their brakes, doesn't use their turn signal, makes traffic all back up behind them, that's not
God causing it. Okay, that's a misuse of their human freedom, okay, in that moment. That's what's
going on. Okay, and then God grants prevenient grace. That's a word that's very important to
this tradition. It means the grace that goes before, the grace that goes beforehand. God
grants provenient grace to all humanity, enabling human free will to respond and receive salvation,
and he then chooses or elects those who he foreknows will respond and accept his grace.
And that's Arminianism. What do both of these agree on? Both of these agree that God is the
primary actor and initiator in history. Humans make real moral choices and are responsible for
them, and humans cannot earn or merit their own salvation. It is only by the grace of God that we
are saved, okay? I'm laying all this out for us here. Partly, I just want you to be familiar with
these things. I actually really, I don't like preaching, I don't like in a sense preaching
theologies. I prefer to just preach the text in front of us, but I know these are things that
people have conversations about and are confused about. Some of you are probably going to look at
this and be like, I think he's wrong about that. Like, you know, whatever, I don't know what I'm
talking about. Okay, let me know afterward, okay? But as we look at all of this, I think, you know,
there are other ways that Christians understand these questions too. There are other views like
Molinism that introduces the idea of like middle knowledge to understand some of this. I'm not
going to get into all of it. But when we look at all of this, we need to really dig into like how
is it that we're understanding God and his sovereignty, his will toward us and the choices
that we make. And ultimately, I would say for myself, for our church, we're going to lean more
toward the reformed side of things there. I think really, again, as I mentioned last week, having a
high view of the sovereignty of God. So, we humans, we still make choices, real choices. God is
ultimately the one who is guiding history, who is making decisions about even our salvation.
Why is that important? As we get into this here, I think a bigger question we should think about is
not just how Christians approach these questions in different ways, but actually, like, how much
better it is to rest in the truth of God's word than to be lost without hope apart from God.
this is something that we need to really dig into and here like we need to really wrestle with like
who we actually are like let me um let me maybe bring it up this way like first thing is I think
we need to be humble enough about our own choices that we realize we make some pretty bad choices
and that we never would have chosen to turn to God on our own we need to be honest and humble
about that. Maybe sometimes we make some good choices. We make a lot of bad ones. And none of
us here, every Christian, regardless of any of this stuff I just shared with you, everybody agrees
that nobody would turn to God on their own. Nobody would do that on their own, no matter how
you think about it. And so maybe think about it this way. If you kind of reflect on who you were
10 years ago and some of the choices you made 10 years ago, like for some of you, that's when
you were like a little kid? Maybe you're like three years old, five years old, seven years old,
something like that. Some of you, maybe you're in middle school or high school. Some of you were in
college 10 years ago. Some of you, maybe you just got married 10 years ago. Think about who you were
10 years ago and some of the choices that you made. And don't you look back at that 10-year younger
version of you? And don't you look at that person and say, oh, young me was so foolish.
man young me like just made some dumb mistakes like i i mean if if only young me knew what i
know today because i'm really know my stuff today and i'm really wise now and i'm really smart now
and i've got this all figured out and man if only 10 year younger me knew what i knew today man
life would be so much better why didn't younger me know what i know now and the thing is 10 years
from now, you're going to look back, and what are you going to see? Oh, so foolish. Why did he make
that dumb choice, that dumb mistake, right? Now, imagine that from God's perspective, because he's
looking through all of human history, and he sees the foolish choices that we make, and he sees that
we're never going to turn to God on our own, and so what does he do? This passage says, in love,
in love for us in love for his children who he cares for so much he reaches in and what no matter
how you understand it through whatever perspective you understand it says god chooses god predestines
because what's the other choice the other choice is that we're never going to choose god and we're
left lost but god says i love you so much that i'm going to make a choice to call you to myself
to say, I'm not going to leave you wandering in your own foolishness, making your own poor choices,
making your own, just making it worse and worse and worse. I'm going to choose you, call you,
even predestine you in whatever way you want to understand it, to come and be my own children.
That's what it is that he wants to do. And when we look at that, to understand, okay, that's like
what God's doing here. We lose sight of that sometimes in the arguments, the fights about
terminology, but God is saying, I love you so much. In love, I'm going to call you to myself.
But not only that, we should also think about this, not just in like bickering between Christian
camps, but also think about like, what's the choice, if you look at this from like a secular
point of view, from an atheistic worldview out in the world around us, what then? Is our path in
life predetermined? We talk about like determinism, things like that. Do we have real choices, real
will, well, I would encourage you, brothers and sisters, take an honest look at that. And even
for some of you here, maybe you're not yet a follower of Jesus, you're thinking about things,
really think about this. Because if you go out and look at the world from a purely secular,
scientific, materialistic point of view, by the way, I think science is great, we're not anti-science,
okay? But if you look purely from a scientific worldview only, then everything in the universe
is the result of cause and effect relationships.
And everything we do is purely deterministic
and we are just cogs in the great machine of the universe.
That's what it is.
And even if you try,
and some people are now trying different things like,
okay, let's introduce chaos theory.
Let's consider things like subatomic fluctuations
and thermal noise
and more stuff that I don't really understand.
Even if we bring that in,
then we're still determined not just mechanistically
but very unpredictably.
And so all these things that bring meaning to life now become completely empty in that worldview.
Love, sacrifice, beauty, anything like that, these are now just evolutionary survival adaptations.
They don't really mean anything.
There's no true resolution to evil or tragedy or injustice.
So none of it means anything anyway.
And the idea that we have free will
or moral responsibility or agency,
these are just neurological delusions.
They're not real.
When we look at the Bible and we see things like this,
we see God's sovereignty, we see how he's made us,
we see how he's redeemed us,
when we look at the Bible this way
and see our relationship with God
and the identity and purpose that he gives us,
then we start to realize, wow, I'm made in the image of God.
I'm not just a material being, I'm a spiritual being.
And God has actually given us a will, a conscience, a soul, a spirit that we're not constrained only by the material cause and effect of the universe.
We can have real relationships and real meaningful choices and our lives have purpose and value because of all of that.
And not only that, evil and suffering and tragedy and injustice, all of that are not final.
because God in his ultimate plan redeems brokenness
and guarantees a final restoration,
a final redemption of all of it.
And so all of this is received through relationship
with our sovereign God who's accomplishing his purposes
and is working all things we see in verse five here
according to the purpose of his will.
Again, we're gonna see that over and over again.
Remember last week, how did Paul become Paul?
It was by the will of God.
How is God working out his plan for the universe, for eternity?
It is according to the purpose of his will.
This is how all these things are playing out.
And this is something God wants us to learn to trust.
To trust, to rest in.
To know, wow, my life has meaning.
God loves me.
God is working in my life.
And the sovereignty of God is actually grounding our human choice,
love, purpose, destiny, all of that is all coming from God and his sovereignty. Okay,
long detour, let's come back. Okay, what are we chosen and predestined for? Does this passage tell
us? What we're chosen and predestined for is to be holy and blameless adopted children.
That's what we're chosen and predestined for. By the way, like I said, we're going to hit those
topics of choice, predestination, election, all of that, all throughout the rest of Ephesians.
We're going to have to keep coming back to it. But the point is, what are we called and
predestined for? To be holy and blameless adopted children. By the way, I just want to point out
here, elsewhere in Ephesians, a lot of other places in the Bible too, you see a lot of things
like adoption of sons, right? And I just want to clarify, Greek, maybe like Spanish or Italian or
or languages like that, French, it's a gendered language. And a lot of times the plural masculine
is used to refer as an umbrella term to masculine and feminine. And so when it says here adopted
as sons, it's not, doesn't, it's not excluding women. Okay. I just want to make sure that that's
clear here. So we look at this, okay, holy and blameless. Are we actually holy and blameless?
no right some of you are like what's the right answer we're not are we we do some pretty messed
up stuff i do all the time we're not we're not actually holy and blameless but are we holy and
blameless in christ is the question yes we are yes we are in christ in christ if we are in christ
we place our faith in him and what he's done then when God looks at us he sees the righteousness of
his son Jesus and in Christ our sin and rebellion against God are atoned for cleansed and forgiven
in Christ we are holy and blameless and because of that we don't relate with God like some kind
of distant judge presiding over an eternal courtroom just waiting to condemn us now because
of that, he's predestined us to be adopted as his adopted children. So now we relate to him as a
loving father who has actually chosen to be in relationship with us. And that's a powerful truth.
I don't know if some of you are familiar with this guy, Scott Hamilton. He's a pretty well-known
Olympian from like decades ago, figure skater. Now he does more like commentating than skating
anymore. But back in his day, he was like an Olympic gold medalist, four-time world champion,
all of that. And he was born actually in Northwest Ohio. We'll forgive him for that. He was born
around Toledo, okay? And when he was born, his parents gave him up for adoption. And he was
adopted by a Christian couple, both teachers, raised him, loved him so well. He just had great
experiences being loved and raised by his parents. But as he grew up, kids at school found out that
he was adopted and started making fun of him for it. Ha ha, Scott, your parents rejected you.
your parents didn't want you, stuff like that, right? And so he goes home and talks to his mom
and says, Mom, this is what kids in the playground are saying. They're saying I was rejected. They're
saying my parents didn't want me. And what should I do? And he said his mom told them, well, next day
when you go to school, they make fun of you like that. You tell them, my parents actually chose me.
Your parents got stuck with whatever they got. That's a little harsh, okay? But hey, I think
it's valid. That's a good response in that situation. But more seriously, he said, I was
chosen. I was wanted. I wasn't an accident. I was an answer to prayer. Do you realize how powerful
that truth is? When God says, I've chosen to adopt you. Like what a powerful thing that is to
know for ourselves and our own value in God's eyes. And by the way, God made this decision we
see here before the foundation of the world. That's a long time ago. It's not based on anything
really about what we have done for ourselves. It's not based on how talented we are, what good grades
we get, how we're doing at work, what our income is, how good you look, how spiritual you are,
how much you pray. It's not based on anything like that. It's just purely God's choice before you
were ever born. Michael Barrett writes it this way. He says, our sonship rests on a love that
never began, as well as a love that will never end. In eternity before the beginning of time,
and obviously before the beginning of us, God chose to make us his children. The gospel was
not God's afterthought or even his forethought. It was his eternal thought. This has been God's
plan forever. And when he looks at us, he says, I'm calling you, I'm choosing you, I'm predestining you
to be my adopted children. That's something that we never could have earned, so we can never lose.
And if we receive that, trust that, trust God's will in this, that leads to such a deep security,
such a deep confidence in who we are in this new identity. And if we know God that way,
if we know that this is his will, his plan, his purpose, his choosing us to be his own children,
well then what's our response to that? Let's hear what we see in this passage as well,
is that our response is to bless and praise God.
Notice that in these verses we've been talking about,
everything we're talking about today
is just wrapped in worship.
From the beginning of the passage,
blessed be the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ,
and toward the end to the praise of his glorious grace.
These are our responses to these beautiful truths
that are being revealed to us here today.
And this is not just how we respond to the beautiful truth
that God has made us as adopted children,
but it's actually also how we live in that truth.
It's not just a response,
it's also how we live in the reality of it.
Like, if I could come back for a second
to this theme of higher calling.
For many of us, when we think calling,
we instantly think of,
what am I supposed to do for God?
And we make it primarily about what we do.
But what this passage is making clear to us here
is that the first and most important thing
is that we are called to relationship with God.
That's the most important thing.
And so this becomes about being before it's ever about doing.
It's knowing who we are in Christ, knowing our relationship with God,
knowing God's grace and God's favor upon us.
When we know that, then out of that comes living who we are in relationship with him.
It's about relationship, not performance or achievement.
And we have to be able to know this and rest in this.
Another quote from Michael Barrett, he says,
in our adoption. Not only does God guarantee for us the legal rights fixing our standing in his
family, but he also brings us home to experience all the benefits of sonship. We are not just sons
of God on paper. We are the sons of God in our daily experience. The tragedy is that so many
believers continue to live in the orphanage without taking advantage of all that belongs to them.
god wants us not just to know these things as information but to actually then live in that
reality in relationship with him and so think about for a second when you read these words on
a page even when i read the passage for us earlier or maybe when you read your daily bible reading
or something when you read the pages of scripture how do you read them and i think for a lot of us
we end up reading the pages of scripture almost like it's like just any other information that
we receive on a daily basis. Like, think about this. For some of us, maybe we read the pages of
scripture almost like reading an Ikea manual. And we're like, okay, like, I'm going to try to follow
the instructions, but I'm probably going to get something out of order somewhere, and I'm going to
get really frustrated. I'm going to have to take it apart and redo it again, and just like, okay,
it's like an instruction manual, and it's frustrating, and it's confusing, and I lost a screw.
Right? It's like, okay, maybe we read it that way. Maybe you read it like the instructions on a pack
of ramen noodles.
And you're like, maybe you're like,
well, I never read those instructions anyway.
I just, I know what I'm doing.
I have my own way.
You're like, I'm not going to read it anyway.
Oh, well, it's old news.
I just do my thing, no matter what.
Or maybe you read it like a parking ticket
that you probably get if you stay around Ann Arbor
long enough.
You see that on your windshield,
lets you know you have a fine.
You're like, okay, now I feel horrible.
I did something wrong.
messed up my day
I feel bad about it
go on with life
we don't realize
that when we read God's word
it isn't presenting us primarily
a to-do list
or an instruction manual
or a fine for doing something wrong
that when we read God's word
and especially passages like this
what we're reading is actually more like an adoption certificate
saying I've chosen you as my own
and when we read that
when we look at something like that.
Our response to that is not like,
okay, nice information, thanks God.
I'll go about my day now.
But there's a joyful response to that.
Not, blessed be the God and Father
of our Lord Jesus Christ.
All these things to the praise
of his glorious grace.
But wow, to the praise of his glorious grace
because of what he's done for me.
And so when we think about that,
recognizing, like we may know
the right information and knowledge,
but are we relationally living in that reality?
And I think this passage is really inviting us
into just a deeper intimacy with the Father,
specifically through worship.
And so as we just kind of get ready
to close out our time here,
can you think about what does that intimacy
with the Father look like?
I'll just show you some pictures here
just to kind of reflect a little bit.
What does it look like to be,
wow, that's going really fast.
You can go slower than that if possible.
We can back that up.
Just think about these scenes for a moment.
And think about what does your intimacy with the Father look like?
Because what God actually desires for us is this closeness to rest on his shoulder,
to enjoy being tossed in the air by him,
to know that we can even be with him in sadness in difficulty so that we can just enjoy looking
in his face to rest in the reality of a loving father who cares for us to be in that kind of
relationship is this what your relationship with the father actually looks like and if it's not
God is not shaking his finger at you saying what's wrong with you God is rather inviting you
That higher calling, again, it's not like,
go get busy for God, go do a bunch of stuff for God.
It's a, come, you're invited in,
your calling first is to be my adopted daughter or son.
Come live in that intimacy, come live in that reality.
Another quote from Alistair McGrath here,
adoption is about being wanted.
It is about belonging.
These are deeply emotive themes
which resonate with the cares and concerns of many
in our increasingly fractured society.
To be adopted is to be invited
into a loving and caring environment.
It is about being welcomed, wanted, and invited.
Adoption celebrates the privilege of invitation
in which the outsider is welcomed
into the fold of faith and love.
This is God's heart for us.
And brothers and sisters, as a church,
I don't want us to just rush forward
into the rest of the year saying,
okay God, show me the great things I'm supposed to do for you. Show me the gifts I'm going to use
for your glory. Show me how you want me to get busy building your kingdom. I don't want us to
rush forward into that without first hearing and responding to God's invitation of a loving
father adopting us into his own family and then us not just knowing that as if God sent us a letter
in the mail because he never wants to see us, but knowing that as a God who face to face
wants to meet with us, wants to have intimate fellowship with us, wants to really live in
the reality of that relationship. And so as we close here, can we maybe one thing to remember
is to rejoice in the blessing of being God's chosen child. Can we rejoice in that blessing
today? And we're going to see more blessings as we go on through the rest of this chapter and into
the rest of the book. But can we start there? God, you've chosen me to be my child. That's
first piece of my inheritance that I received from you. And God, now I want to live in that.
And a couple things specifically I would really encourage you with today is, number one,
like know who you are in Christ. And we're going to explore that through Ephesians. We get to talk
about that here on Sunday and our life groups, all of that. But as we talk about that together,
maybe you want to dig in deeper. Use some of those resources I shared with you earlier.
Because this is probably the most important thing to living a fruitful Christian life is to know
who you are in Christ.
So maybe go through and take
like one verse on one
of those resources I shared with you
and journal about that and
pray through that and celebrate
that in your own relationship with
God. That would be so transformative
for us. And secondly, a second
encouragement is just to make space for intimacy
with God. So again, God
does not just want us to know the right information
like some
kind of set of instructions.
He wants us to have that
space for true intimacy with him.
That can look like a lot of things, but I would
encourage you, even when you do things, like maybe you're
following our church's Bible reading plan, like really
dig into that and say, God, through this
I want a deeper relationship
with you. Maybe it's personal time
of worship. Just when you're alone at home,
God, I want to spend this time just seeking
you, living in close fellowship with
you. Maybe like some of those pictures we were just
reflecting on.
Maybe even corporately, it's things like, I'm so
encouraged actually, when I come in on Sunday morning,
we have our pre-celebration prayer time
10 minutes before we get started
and seeing a good chunk of you coming in early
to use that time to prepare your heart for worship
because this time when we gather for worship
this isn't just like kind of
kind of like filler time
when we just need to fill the time
where we wait for everybody to arrive
no this is space to meet with God
this is space to be in his presence
to seek his face
to say God I want that deeper fellowship with you
maybe even things like we do together
like prayer gathering stuff like that
that's helpful to create these spaces for intimacy,
whether personally or together.
God's heart for us is to welcome us
into that close fellowship with him.
We wanna be able to rise into that as our higher calling
and live in that truth together.
Can we stand together?
And we'll spend some time in response today.